Agnes Rindge Claflin Concerning Alexander Calder
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Agnes Rindge Claflin papers concerning Alexander Calder
1936-circa 1970s
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Claflin, Agnes Rindge
23 folders
The papers of arts administrator, collector, and educator Agnes Rindge Claflin concerning Alexander Calder are comprised of 28 items and date from 1936-circa 1970s. Included are five letters, two of which are illustrated, and one postcard from Alexander Calder to Claflin; two handwritten manuscripts by Calder, one untitled and "A Propos of Measuring a Mobile," 1943; an invitation to a Calder exhibition at Galerie Maeght, Paris, 1952; and 14 photographs of Calder, of Calder and Claflin in Calder's studio, of Calder's art work, and of a Calder exhibition installation at Vassar Art Gallery, 1942. Transcriptions of three of the letters and both manuscripts are also included.
Provenance
The collection was donated in 1981 by Philip W. Claflin, widower of Agnes Rindge Claflin.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds several collections related to the Agnes Rindge Claflin papers concerning Alexander Calder, including the Alexander Calder papers which have been fully digitized; Alexander Calder letters and photographs microfilmed on reel 4781; Alexander Calder letter microfilmed on reel 2787, frames 963-970; and an oral history interview with Alexander Calder, October 26, 1971, available as a transcript online.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection was digitized in 2010 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Agnes Rindge Claflin (1900-1977) was an arts administrator, collector, and educator who spent the majority of her career at Vassar College as a professor and serving as director of its art gallery for 28 years.
Claflin was born Agnes Millicent Rindge in Grand Rapids, Michigan on May 19, 1900. She graduated from the Madeira School in 1917, attended Mount Holyoke College for two years, and graduated magna cum laude from Radcliffe College. Afterwards, Claflin briefly taught at Vassar College before returning to Radcliffe and earning her M.A. and Ph.D. She rejoined the Vassar College faculty in 1928 and served as the director of the Vassar Art Gallery from 1934-1962. Claflin published Sculpture in 1929 and in the 1930s she began writing articles for several different publications. At the request of Alfred Barr, she joined the Advisory Committee for the Museum of Modern Art in 1941 and became the Assistant Executive Vice President from 1943-1944. Claflin held a number of other positions in art organizations such as the Commission on Arts of the American Association of Colleges (1939), Art in America (1940-1943), Art Division of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs (1941-1942), American Federation of Arts (1944-1945), and Committee on Fellowships of the College Art Association (1945-1948). She married Philip W. Claflin, a captain in the U.S. Army, in 1945. Throughout her career, Claflin lectured at organizations and universities across the United States, including the Chicago Art Institute, Columbia University, New York University, Yale University, and many others. Agnes Claflin died on June 12, 1977.
Claflin and Calder were colleagues and friends. In 1942, the Vassar Art Gallery hosted a Calder exhibition installation. The following year, Claflin wrote and narrated a short film, "Alexander Calder: Sculpture and Constructions," which was presented with the Museum of Modern Art's Calder exhibition of the same year.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of arts administrator, collector, and educator Agnes Rindge Claflin concerning Alexander Calder are comprised of 28 items and date from 1936-circa 1970s. Included are five letters and one postcard from Alexander Calder to Claflin, two of which are illustrated; two handwritten manuscripts by Calder, one untitled and "A Propos of Measuring a Mobile," 1943; an invitation to a Calder exhibition at Galerie Maeght, Paris, 1952; and 14 photographs of Calder, of Calder and Claflin in Calder's studio, of Calder's art work, and of a Calder exhibition installation at Vassar Art Gallery, 1942. One photograph depicting an event is possibly the opening of the Calder exhibition at Vassar Art Gallery, 1942. Also included are two polaroid photographs most likely from the 1970s. Transcriptions of three of the letters and both manuscripts are also included.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of the collection, items are organized into one series of 23 folders:
Series 1: Agnes Rindge Claflin Papers Concerning Alexander Calder, 1936-circa 1970s (Box 1; 23 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976; Vassar College -- Art Gallery
Subjects-Topical:
Art -- Collectors and collecting; Arts administrators -- New York (State)
Types of Materials:
Illustrated letters; Manuscripts; Photographs; Potcards
Names:
Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Agnes Rindge Claflin Papers Concerning Alexander Calder, 1936-circa 1970s, Series 1:; (Box 1; 23 folders)
  If a document has a transcription, it can be found in the same folder as the original document. This collection has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Letter, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter, 1936, June 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter, 1942, March 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter, 1942, May 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter, 1945, March 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter, 1954, December 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript about Sculpture, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "A Propos of Measuring a Mobile" Manuscript, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Invitation, Galerie Maeght, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photograph of Event, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photograph of Calder/Miro Exhibition at Vassar Art Gallery, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photograph of Calder/Miro Exhibition at Vassar Art Gallery, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photograph of Calder/Miro Exhibition at Vassar Art Gallery, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photograph of Calder/Miro Exhibition at Vassar Art Gallery, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photograph of Calder/Miro Exhibition at Vassar Art Gallery, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photograph of Mobile Sculpture, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photograph of Calder's Studio, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photograph of Calder & Claflin, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photograph of Calder & Claflin in Calder's Studio, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photograph of Calder & Claflin in Calder's Studio, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photograph of Calder & Claflin, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Polaroid Photograph of Sculpture, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Polaroid Photograph of Package, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 23)
Other Finding Aid
Bibliography